Leah: Stacks, Queues and Lists are
more or less what they sound like.
Jack: Firstly, a Stack is
the simplest grouping of data
and also the most important.
Like in everyday life, a stack is a
group of objects stacked into a pile
and just as you wouldn’t pull the bottom
book out of a stack of books, the top
object in the stack or the last one
added, is always first to be removed.
This principle is referred to
as LIFO or Last in First Out.
So, the book or object in this case
that was last added to the stack,
would be the first to get removed.
A great example of a stack is the undo
button or back button on a browser,
when clicked, you want to go back to
the last state or page, not the first.
Leah: A Queue is similar to a
stack in that it is a grouping
of data but is different in the
method that data is retrieved.
It works the same as in real life
for example when a queue is formed of
people waiting for something, the last
to join would not be the first to go.
This is the same in coding, a
principle is used which is referred
to as FIFO or First in First Out.
The object in this case that is first
to enter the queue is the first to exit.
A great example of a Queue is a
call waiting system at a call centre
where you want the first people who
dialled in, being the first callers
that are handled by your team.
Jack: A Linear List is a more
memory intensive and a complicated
version of a stack or queue.
While a stack or queue is only
ever as large as the objects
stacked or queued together, a list
is a prescribed amount of space.
Just think about save slots for a game,
usually there is a set amount, and if
a player only ever saves their game
in the same slot overwriting their
previous save, all the memory allocated
to those other slots is sat wasted.
Conversely if a player keeps saving
in a new slot each time, eventually
they will run out of slots so will
be unable to save any newer saves
without replacing older ones.